Chris: So, what is meant by
Configuration Management?
Configuration management is a process that
defines, controls, documents, and reports
the ‘configuration items’ in a system.
It was created to maintain consistency,
ensuring that the systems used to create
the product, perform as they are expected to
as changes are made throughout, essentially
a way to manage a system configuration.
Configuration management is a key part of
the ‘DevOps lifecycle’, and ‘Continuous
Integration/Continuous Delivery’, or CI/CD
can be set up so change requests can be
automatically deployed, to an existing system.
Configuration management works well with the
‘Agile methodology’ as it supports ‘Agile
teams’ to ‘prioritise’ configuration tasks.
Leah: Software Configuration Management
or SCM is a process to manage, organise,
and control the changes that occur in the
different aspects, such as code, documents,
and other entities during a software project.
Most large software projects would have a ‘SCM
co-ordinator’, to manage the process, as it
could become quite complex given the number
of changes that would be made to the code.
The ‘SCM co-ordinator’ would use
automated tools to support the process.
Chris: Good SCM would ensure that all changes are
documented, consistent, compliant, and stable.
A SCM system would define the system
settings; and would then build and maintain
those systems according to the settings.
It helps users know the current
state of a software product.
This prevents issues so there are not as
many problems that could occur later in the
project, such as code conflicts when there is
more than one Coder working on the same code.
It also helps to ensure that the testing
and production environments match up
and supports automation which would
reduce costs, complexity, and errors.
Leah: A SCM system would have a set of software
tools which would be used to track and control
changes in the stages of a software project.
SCM tools are used to store the current state
of a system and help to maintain that state.
They are used to support faster
changes and deployments and remove the
potential for errors, making system
management, predictable and scalable.
They also keep track of resources
and avoid task repetition.
A SCM tool would improve a system recovery
with its automation capabilities, as
it would also keep an audit trail which
would document any changes or updates.
Therefore, if a system failed or
crashed, the reason could be identified
and avoided in future deployments.
Chris: Another configuration tool that is used,
is a Configuration Management Database or CMDB.
This database helps to
manage configuration assets.
It stores the configuration records for
the assets, and includes the attributes,
such as type, owner, or version.
It also stores the relationships
with other assets in the system.
In a software project ‘SCM tools’
would be expected to include:
• Asset management, the storing, classifying,
and managing of configuration assets.
• Track changes, a version control system
would be used to track code changes.
• Deployment, which would be automated from
the Continuous Delivery or ‘CD’ stage.
• Configuration comparison, allowing
the current state to be compared
to the previous state if needed.
• Leah: Automated routine tasks, such
as running system patches and updates.
• Configuration backup and recovery,
meaning the system can be restored
from a backup If there are any issues.
This would also be related to version
control and rollback strategy.
• Visual dashboard, ensuring visibility and
ease of use for all members of the team,
including the ‘Configuration co-ordinator’,
the ‘Developer team’, and the ‘Project manager’
• Chris: Performance monitoring, identifying poor
performing and noncompliant configurations.
• Troubleshooting, such as
identifying bugs or code conflicts.
• Security, ensuring that the
system is secure and protected.
• Analytics, so that reports can be generated
to resolve issues and for project planning.
Leah: There are several ‘SCM tools’ on the
market today, that can be used, including open
source and commercial brands, let’s look at
some examples and don’t forget you can check out
our weblinks in this session to find out more:
• Auvik - cloud-based Network
and Monitoring software
• Ansible - IT Automation Framework
• CFEngine - Configuration tool which
is both open source and commercial.
• Chef - IT Automation Framework
• Chris: Endpoint Central - Unified
Endpoint Management or UEM solution
• Docker - Containerisation configuration management
• Git – Distributed Version control system
• Puppet - IT Automation Framework
• Terraform - Configuration management
platform which is open source
Leah: The tools that are selected for use,
would depend on the type of the software project
and size of the team, and it is important to
remember that they would be part of a wider
Software configuration management system.
Therefore, in most cases there would
be more than one tool used such as
‘version control’ and ‘deployment’.